Guide to the John W. Freeman papers, 1965-1979 MS 344
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
John W. Freeman Papers
1965-1979
1965-1971
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Freeman, John W.
MS 344
11 Linear Feet (10 boxes)
The collection consists of reports, photographs, and films related to the NASA Suprathermal Ion Detector Experiment (SID), part of the Apollo Lunar Surface Experiment Package (ALSEP). This experiment, involving equipment developed by Freeman, was part of the work of Apollo missions 12, 14, and 15.
Biographical note: John W. Freeman
Dr. John W. Freeman, professor emeritus and research professor of physics and astronomy, is a former NASA scientist and a long time professor at Rice University in the Space Sciences Department. During the Apollo missions of the 1960's and 1970's Dr. Freeman was instrumental in the development of the Suprathermal Ion Detector Experiment, and for this effort was awarded the NASA Medal for Exceptional Scientific Achievement in 1973. Dr. Freeman was also involved in the Rice University solar power satellite research program; one of his two patents is a solar energy conversion device for space. He is also the author of a book published in 2001 titled Storms in Space and numerous papers and articles. In 2005 Dr. Freeman became the first director of the Master of Liberal Studies program at the School of Continuing Studies at Rice.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of materials related to the NASA Suprathermal Ion Detector Experiment, part of the Apollo Lunar Surface Experiment Package (ALSEP), and includes documents and photographs from Apollo missions 11, 12, 14, and 15. The materials include glossy photographs from Apollo missions; publications and engineering reports; eleven color and seven black and white positive transparencies of 70 mm film; five 16mm silent films from NASA; and twelve oversize black and white print posters of the lunar surface. The collection is in good shape generally. The reports which were bound in metal acco fasteners and staples show some deterioration, and some of the rolls of 70 mm film show signs of moisture damage. The 16 mm films are in good shape; no sign of deterioration. The oversize pictures of the lunar surface are somewhat frayed on the edges.
Conditions Governing Access
Boxes 1-8 stored off-site at the Library Service Center. Please request this material via woodson@rice.edu or call 713-348-2586.
Boxes 9-10 stored onsite at the Woodson Research Center.
Access Restrictions
This material is open for research but requires 24 hours for retrieval. Please call ahead at 713-348-2586 or email the staff at woodson@rice.edu.
Source of Acquisition
This collection was a gift donated by Dr. John W. Freeman, January 11, 1982.
Index Terms
Subjects
Apollo Spacecraft; Apollo Lunar Surface Experiments Package; Lunar exploration; Manned space flight
- Series I. Apollo Missions 11-15 and Apollo Lunar Surface Experiments Package, 1969-1971; 37964
  - Subseries A: Apollo Saturn Mission Photographs (descriptions of photographs are included in file 1 of each document box), 1969-1971; 37969 (Box 1-3)
    - Apollo Saturn Missions 11 and 12 photographs, 1969; 37986 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Apollo Saturn Mission 12 photographs, 1969; 38003 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Apollo Saturn Missions 12 and 14 photographs, 1969, 1971; 38004 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Apollo Saturn Mission 14 photographs, 1971; 38005 (Box 1, Folder 4-35)
    - Apollo Saturn Mission 14 photographs, 1971; 38007 (Box 2, Folder 1-9)
    - Apollo Saturn Missions 14 and 15 photographs, 1971; 38008 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Apollo Saturn Mission 15 photographs, 1971; 38009 (Box 2, Folder 11-50)
    - Apollo Saturn Mission 15 photographs, 1971; 38010 (Box 3, Folder 1-39)
- Series II. NASA Apollo and Saturn Mission publications and Time Zero Corporation Apollo Lunar Surface Experiments Package/ Suprathermal Ion Detector Experiment/ Cold Cathode Gauge Experiment (ALSEP/ SIDE/ CCGE) publications, 1966-1979; 41153
  - Subseries A: NASA Publications, 1964-1979; 37970 (Box 4)
    - NASA Manned Spacecraft Center. Analysis of Apollo 8: Photography and Visual Observations. National Aeronautics and Space Administration. Washington, D.C., 1969; 38011 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - NASA. Saturn V Flight Manual, SA 509. National Aeronautics and Space Administration. Washington, D.C., 1971; 38012 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Morse, Mary Louise, and Jean K. Bays. The Apollo Spacecraft: A Chronology. Volume II. November 8, 1962 to September 30, 1964. Washington, D.C. National Aeronautics and Space Administration., 1973; 38013 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Brooks, Courtney G., and Ivan D. Ertel. The Apollo Spacecraft: A Chronology. Volume III. October 1, 1964 to January 20, 1966. Washington, D.C.National Aeronautics and Space Administration., 1976; 38014 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Ertel, Ivan D., and Roland W. Newkirk. The Apollo Spacecraft: A Chronology. Volume IV. January 21, 1966 to July 13, 1974. Washington, D.C. National Aeronautics and Space Administration., 1978; 38015 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Bates, James R., W. W. Lauderdale, and Harold Kernaghan. Apollo Lunar Surface Experiments Package (ALSEP) Termination Report. Washington, D.C. National Aeronautics and Space Administration., 1979; 38016 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Subseries B: NASA Publications and Engineering Reports, 1966-1970, n.d.; 37979 (Box 5)
    - NASA Manned Spacecraft Center. Apollo Lunar Landing Mission Symposium, Volume I. Houston, TX. National Aeronautics and Space Administration., 1966; 38017 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - NASA Manned Spacecraft Center. Apollo Lunar Landing Mission Symposium, Volume II. Houston, TX. National Aeronautics and Space Administration., 1966; 38018 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - NASA Manned Spacecraft Center. Apollo Lunar Landing Mission Symposium, Volume III. Houston, TX. National Aeronautics and Space Administration., 1966; 38019 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Time-Zero Corporation. Apollo Lunar Surface Experiments Package/ Suprathermal Ion Detector Experiment/Cold Cathode Gauge Experiment (ALSEP/ SIDE/CCGE) Final Engineering Report, Volume 1.1, Houston, TX., 38020 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Time-Zero Corporation. Apollo Lunar Surface Experiments Package/ Suprathermal Ion Detector Experiment/Cold Cathode Gauge Experiment (ALSEP/ SIDE/CCGE) Final Engineering Report, Volume 1.2, Houston, TX., 38021 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Time-Zero Corporation. Apollo Lunar Surface Experiments Package/ Suprathermal Ion Detector Experiment/Cold Cathode Gauge Experiment (ALSEP/ SIDE/CCGE) Final Engineering Report, Volume 2.1, Houston, TX., 38022 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Time-Zero Corporation. Apollo Lunar Surface Experiments Package/ Suprathermal Ion Detector Experiment/Cold Cathode Gauge Experiment (ALSEP/ SIDE/CCGE) Final Engineering Report, Volume 2.2, Houston, TX., 38023 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - NASA Marshal Space Flight Center. Saturn V Launch Vehicle Flight Evaluation Report AS-508, Apollo 13 Mission. Huntsville, AL: National Aeronautics and Space Administration., 1970; 38024 (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Series III. Proposals and technical drawings for the Apollo Lunar Surface Experiment Package/ Suprathermal Ion Detector (ALSEP/SID) and Rice University Solar Power Satellite Research Program documents, 1965-1979; 41154
  - Subseries A: Technical Drawings and Proposals, 1965-1979; 37980 (Box 6)
    - Marshall Laboratories drawings, Suprathermal Ion experiment, No. 51712-schematic test set., 1965; 38025 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Marshall Laboratories drawings, Suprathermal Ion experiment, No. 51774-panel test set., 1965; 38026 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Proposal 7065: Marshall Laboratories Technical plan for the Apollo Lunar Surface Experiment Package/ Suprathermal Ion Detector (ALSEP/SID) Volume 1., 1965; 38027 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Proposal 7065: Marshall Laboratories Technical plan for the Apollo Lunar Surface Experiment Package/ Suprathermal Ion Detector (ALSEP/SID) Volume 2., 1965; 38028 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Bendix Corporation drawings: Proposal 3195 Suprathermal Ion experiment., 1966; 38029 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Bendix Corporation: Proposal 3195 Suprathermal Ion experiment., 1966; 38030 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Rice University Solar Power Satellite Research Program., 1977-1979; 38031 (Box 6, Folder 7)
- Series IV. Apollo Missions 10, 11, 12, 14, and 15: Black and white and color positive film transparencies, slides, and 16mm silent film, 1969-1971; 41156
  - Subseries A: NASA Lunar Mission Films, Slides, and Transparencies, 1969-1971; 37981 (Box 7)
    - Carton. Apollo 15 Mission: 7 rolls of black/white positive transparencies, 70 mm film., July 26, 1971- August 7, 1971; 38032 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Carton. Apollo 12 Mission: 6 rolls of color positive transparencies, 70 mm film. (Rolls 2.1, 2.2, and 2.3 show signs of moisture damage.), November 14,1969- November 24, 1969; 38033 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Carton. Apollo 14 Mission: 4 rolls of color positive transparencies, 70 mm film. (Roll 3.1 shows signs of moisture damage.), January 31, 1971- February 9, 1971; 38034 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Carton. Apollo 15 Mission: 1 roll of color positive transparencies, 70 mm film. (Roll shows signs of moisture damage.), July 26, 1971- August 7, 1971; 38035 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Carton. Apollo 12 mission: NASA 16mm silent film. Black/white print containing view of the moon., November 14,1969-November 24, 1969; 38036 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Carton. Apollo 12 mission: NASA 16mm silent film. Color print of rendezvous of the 2 space capsules; work on the calibration of the suprathermal ion detector., November 14, 1969- November 24, 1969; 38037 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Carton. Apollo 14 mission: NASA 16mm silent film. Lunar landing, flag raising, equipment display by astronauts; lift-off from the lunar surface., January 31, 1971- February 9, 1971; 38038 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Carton. Apollo 15 mission: NASA 16mm silent film. Descent; flipping of weightless objects in space capsule (5-71-263)., July 26, 1971- August 7, 1971; 38039 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Carton. Apollo 15 mission: NASA 16mm silent film. View of the lunar surface (ascent) (5-71-276)., July 26, 1971- August 7, 1971; 38040 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Carton. Apollo 10 mission: NASA slides of the mission, May 18-26, 1969 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Carton. Apollo 11 mission: NASA slides of the mission, July 16-24, 1969 (Box 7, Folder 11)
- Series V. Oversize black and white posters of LRC Lunar Orbital Project- Mission II and III and duplicate photographs of Apollo Saturn Missions 14 and 15, 1966-1971; 41157
  - Subseries A: Oversize Prints and Duplicate Photographs, 1966-1971; 37982 (Oversize 8)
    - Oversize box. Apollo Saturn Missions 14 and 15 duplicate photographs, 1971; 38041 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Oversize box. NASA – LRC Lunar Orbiter Project- Mission II: 5 oversize black and white posters, 1966; 38042 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Oversize box. NASA – LRC Lunar Orbiter Project- Mission III: 7 oversize black and white posters, 1967; 38043 (Box 8, Folder 3)
- Series VI. Model of experiment, 1969 - 1971; 160572
  - Mechanical model of Suprathermal Ion Detector, 1969-1971; 160573 (Box 9)
  - Mechanical model of Suprathermal Ion Detector - antenna, 1969-1971 (Box 10)